Preliminary Guide to the Albert J. Solnit Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Albert J. Solnit papers
1952-2001
MS 1809
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
12.5
(9 boxes)
The papers consist of Solnit's resource and writings files concerning subjects of prime interest to him, such as child development, parenting, adoption, and custody. The papers also include audio and video recordings of Solnit's lectures and photographs.
Solnit, Albert J., 1919-2002
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Ben Solnit, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Biographical / Historical
Albert J. Solnit was born on August 26, 1919, in Los Angeles, California. He completed his undergraduate education and medical training at the University of California, Berkeley and served as a psychiatrist in the U. S. Army Air Forces before coming to Yale University in 1948. In 1960, he was named professor of pediatrics and psychiatry. Solnit served as director of the Child Study Center (1966-1983) and was a tireless advocate for the needs of children. He chaired the Connecticut Advisory Council on Children and Youth Services and was commissioner of the Connecticut State Department of Mental Health and Addiction Services (1991-2000). He served as managing editor of "The Psychoanalytic Study of the Child" and wrote important books on family law and psychology and child custody and placement issues. Solnit died as the result of a car accident on June 21, 2002.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of Solnit's resource and writings files concerning subjects of prime interest to him, such as child development, parenting, adoption, and custody. The papers also include audio and video recordings of Solnit's lectures and photographs.
Adoption; Child development; Child psychology; Solnit, Albert J., 1919-2002; Yale University. Child Study Center
- Inventory
  - Anna Freud, 1968-1972 (Box 1)
  - Curriculum vitae, 1999-2001 (Box 1)
  - Compleat Pediatricians, 1970-2000 (Box 1)
  - Seminars and special lectures, Circa 1977-1988 (Box 1)
  - Children in traction study, 1964 (Box 1)
  - Writings sorted by topic (Box 1)
    - Adolescence, 1969-1985 (Box 2)
    - Adoption and best interests of the child, 1980-1997 (Box 2)
    - Aggression, 1966-1978 (Box 2)
    - Best interests of the child, 1979-1985 (Box 3)
    - Child abuse, 1977-1985 (Box 3)
    - Child advocacy, 1985 (Box 3)
    - Child development, 1981-1983 (Box 3)
    - Child development -mental health, 1955-1985 (Box 3)
    - Child placement issues, 1975-1983 (Box 3)
    - Child placement issues, 1977-1986 (Box 4)
    - Child rearing and child advocacy; Child and parents, 1975-1982 (Box 4)
    - Children's rights, 1974-1985 (Box 4)
    - Day care (and treatment), 1991 (Box 4)
    - Death, 1968-1985 (Box 4)
    - Divorce and custody, 1978-1984 (Box 4)
    - Divorce and custody, 1983-1984 (Box 5)
    - Education, 1954-1987 (Box 5)
    - Family, 1975-1979 (Box 5)
    - Family support, 1975-1979 (Box 5)
    - Freud, 1984 (Box 5)
    - Holocaust, 1977-1985 (Box 5)
    - Hospital and children, 1970-1981 (Box 5)
    - Infancy -risk and vulnerability, 1975-1983 (Box 5)
    - Infantile neurosis, 1952-1977 (Box 5)
    - Meditation, n. d. (Box 5)
    - Mental health, 1978, 1991 (Box 5)
    - Object constancy, 1981-1986 (Box 5)
    - Object constancy, 1982-1985 (Box 6)
    - Parenthood, 1972-1973 (Box 6)
    - Pediatrics, 1975-1977 (Box 6)
    - Prevention, 1971-1979 (Box 6)
    - Psychiatry Board of Review, 1979 (Box 6)
    - Psychoanalysis, n. d. (Box 6)
    - Psychoanalysis and child development research, 1983 (Box 6)
    - Psychoanalytic education, 1979-1994 (Box 6)
    - Residential treatment, 1980 (Box 6)
    - Television, 1979-1981 (Box 6)
    - Trauma, 1979-1984 (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1971, n. d. (Box 6)
    - Clippings, 1966-1982 (Box 7)
    - Photographs, 1960s-1990s (Box 7)
    - Audio and video tapes, 1989-1995 (Box 8)
      Conditions Governing Access
      Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers must consult use copies, or if none exist must pay for a use copy, which is retained by the repository. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
    - Memorabilia, 1970, 1972, 1985, undated (Box 9)